[SPEAKER_01]: This is from the Anguttara Nikaya.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's called Disenchantment.
[SPEAKER_01]: Bhikkhu's these five things, when developed and cultivated, lead exclusively to disenchantment, to dispassion, to cessation, to peace, to direct knowledge, to enlightenment, to nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: What five?
[SPEAKER_01]: Here, Bhikkhu dwells contemplating the unattractiveness of the body, perceiving the repulsiveness of food,
[SPEAKER_01]: Perceiving non-delight in the entire world, contemplating impermanence in all conditioned phenomena, and he has the perception of death well established eternally, internally.
[SPEAKER_01]: These five things, when developed and cultivated, lead exclusively to disenchantment, to dispassion, cessation, peace to acknowledge.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nibbāna,
[SPEAKER_01]: And this is again from the Guta.
[SPEAKER_01]: And what, Ananda, is the perception of unattractiveness?
[SPEAKER_01]: Here, Bhikkhu reviews this body upward from the soles of the feet, and downward from the tips of the hairs, enclosed in skin as full of many kinds of impurities.
[SPEAKER_01]: There are in this body hair of the head, hair of the body, nails, teeth, skin, flesh, sinews, bone, bone marrow, kidneys, heart, liver, spleen, lungs, intestines, stomach, excrement, bile, phlegm, pus, blood, sweat, fat, tears, grease, saliva, snot, fluid, joints and urine.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, he dwells contemplating unattractiveness in the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: This is called the perception of unattractiveness.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, this is in regard to the Subha meditation, or meditation on the unattractiveness.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you said yesterday, you were talking about it, and you said that
[SPEAKER_01]: Establishing one's mind on a subha, and then making it endure, without losing sight of the peripheral of that subha, even when sensual inclination is present internally or externally.
[SPEAKER_01]: But maybe we said more.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, it comes down to... the main point of that is basically, you cannot be attracted
[SPEAKER_00]: and repelled by the same thing at the same time.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if that which attracts you, repels you, then you'll be repelled, the attraction will cease.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's important thing to realize, because when you read out the bit from Anguttara Nikaya, where the Buddha recommends, like, reviewing your body in terms of what it's made of,
[SPEAKER_00]: It's very easy to do that wrongly, in a sense of you keep bringing the new things, new objects of your perceptions into your mind, and then trying to kind of, sort of, generate a sense of disgust and dispassion.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, the thing is... the point is not to find things that are disgusting as a replacement to things that are attractive.
[SPEAKER_00]: The point is to see things that are attractive as underlined by a disgusting things, by things that are repelling, by things that are non-attractive.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you need to see they're simultaneously present there, just on a different level.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it's easily... you can easily force yourself to not look at the attractive and just focus on non-attractive, but sooner or later, when you're tired, when your mindfulness lapses, when attractive arises, again, you have no... no... no protection against it, because all you're used to is doing, like, sort of replacing it, and pushing it away, and getting the non-attractive, because you were told that's what you need to do.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, actually, the Buddha never said you need to replace it.
[SPEAKER_00]: He said you need to see it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You need to see it in relation to that which is attractive.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when you're reviewing your body, for example, to get that sense of dispassion, because it's all of your organs, all of the organs by themselves, are not, you know, they're quite repulsive, actually, and certainly not attractive.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's easily seen.
[SPEAKER_00]: But what is hard to see is that, when you are attracted,
[SPEAKER_00]: So, either towards gaining physical pleasure, towards pursuing the objects of physical pleasure externally, you want to see that all of those experiences of sensuality, basically, as fundamentally inseparable from these disgusting organs, and fundamentally
[SPEAKER_00]: So, a person who has truly experienced dispassion and developed it, for them, things are very dispassionate and maybe slightly less dispassionate.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or rather, very unattractive and slightly less unattractive.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sensuality, the beautiful things become slightly less unattractive.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can still recognize the beauty, but none of it is the attractive beauty that would induce sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's ugly and less ugly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: It comes down to that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not like ugly and beautiful that you're just trying to kind of revolve around.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, you know, in order to see the the beautiful as ugly, is you need to see that it's...
[SPEAKER_00]: It's simultaneously and inseparably bound up with those repulsive aspects, that are kind of inseparable from, inescapable from.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why once the mind is experienced through this passion, that order of which comes first, ugly or beautiful, cannot be changed anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: The beautiful cannot step outside of ugly ever again and assume its own, you know, privileged kind of sensual existence.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's how sensuality ceases as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: When it becomes fully enclosed in ugly and you lose entire dispassion for any aspect of sensuality conceivable, possible.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because in its nature, you've seen it's just inconceivable without the basis of ugly.
[SPEAKER_00]: And as such, it's ugly in itself.
[SPEAKER_01]: The danger becomes apparent once dispassion has been developed.
[SPEAKER_00]: Otherwise, you can't grasp the danger.
[SPEAKER_00]: But once you experience dispassion, and the mind has truly, sort of,
[SPEAKER_00]: We're drawn from the perversion of perception, which is what sensuality is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Perceiving ugly is beautiful, and it's easy for what it is, ugly and just slightly less ugly, but equally not wanted.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, you recognize, wow, what a danger it is to actually keep focusing on the less ugly and regarding it as beautiful, because it keeps you bound to the entire thing that is subject to this complete annihilation eventually.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sickness, aging, and death, and then repeat, and again, and again, and again.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just because of that tiny little perversion, just because of your tiny little assumption in thinking that sensual...
[SPEAKER_00]: That beautiful objects of senses can exist separate from the repulsive, non-attractive, disgusting foundations that they are.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why it's important not to keep contemplating the repulsive kind of before or after or trying to replace the beautiful sensual thoughts with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You want to see them.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you need to contemplate, but you need to see it at the same time.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yes, think about the repulsive things of the body, so that you can experience dispassion.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then you have to apply, or rather maintain, that dispassion.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why I said that your perception must learn how to endure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even when sensuality arises, whereby you don't just jump on sensuality and try to get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that wasn't you doing to begin with.
[SPEAKER_00]: What you're doing is, whether you choose to abandon attending the foundations of that sensuality and give to rise to attending pleasing and like temporary sort of particular features of it, which is basically how sensual thoughts originate and they get maintained.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you don't want to keep replacing sensuality, you want to see through it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, all of those things, the disgusting contemplations and so on, that the Buddha was encouraging monks to do, need to be seen through the sensual, through the beautiful objects, through the beautiful things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not instead.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you're not saying that one should go and try and seek out beautiful sights?
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, no, on the contrary.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, if you... if you are seeking out the beautiful sights, means there is no establishment of the right... means the perception is already perverted, which means the mind is not seeing, not attending to the roots of dispassion, roots of disgusting aspects of that sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you don't... you don't need to... you need to restrain the senses first, fully, stop giving in to the habit of seeking pleasure by default, for these roots to be able to be seen through the arisen sensual prospect in a form of thought or a possibility or intention.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if your intention habitually leads you to immediately give in to the action by your senses and seek out the pleasure,
[SPEAKER_00]: No amount of transparency through it will be possible, because you just you just went off, went off with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yeah, that's sometimes people think, oh, I must expose myself sensuality to prove, but if you need to prove to yourself, that you're free from sensuality, means you don't know it, means you doubt it, which means you're not free.
[SPEAKER_00]: If the doubt can enter it, there is no freedom there.
[SPEAKER_00]: And in the same sense, in order to be able to seek sensuality, even as a proof,
[SPEAKER_00]: It requires perversion of perception.
[SPEAKER_00]: It requires sensual perceptions to be established.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means, even if you're seeking out to prove it to yourself, means you're seeking out of sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, no seeking out, seeking out whatsoever, and then seeing through whatever's present, however it's present, however beautiful it might be, you see it inseparable from those ugly aspects that you have been contemplating.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because they're there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the sensuality, the sensual beauty is actually ugly and disgusting and inseparable from disgusting things, unattractive things, that's why freedom from sensuality is possible.
[SPEAKER_00]: If it were truly beautifully, beautiful and independent, you wouldn't be able to go out of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then, it wouldn't be a problem either.
[SPEAKER_00]: You wouldn't have to go out of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's not truly beautiful.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a mistake based on ignorance,
[SPEAKER_00]: Based on sensual craving, based on the fire of lust and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why it's a problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why pleasure underlined by craving is a problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: Pleasure without underlined craving is not a problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: But there is no sensual pleasure that it's not underlined by desire for more lust and greed and craving.